Thank you Jesus.
>> I want to thank you Lord for all you got
for me. Thank you. Thank you Jesus. I
want to thank you Lord for all you got
for me. All I want to do thank you. All
I want to do is thank you Jesus. I want
to thank you Lord for all you.
Thank you.
I want to thank you for
>> All right. Let's give them another round
of applause.
All right. Again, happy Sabbath,
everybody.
>> Happy Sabbath. Uh we're going to go
ahead and we're going to open up. We
read the law every Sabbath. So if you
turn your Bible to Exodus chapter 20,
we're going to read verse 1-1 17. Exodus
chapter 20 verse 1-1 17.
Once you get there, bro, you can go
ahead and read it. And God spake all
these words, saying, I am the Lord thy
God, which have brought thee out of the
land of Egypt, out of the house of
bondage. Thou shalt have no other gods
before me. Thou shalt not make unto thee
any grave graven image or any likeness
of anything that is in heaven above, or
that is in the earth beneath, or that is
in the water under the earth. Thou shalt
not bow down thyself to them, nor serve
them. I the Lord thy God am a jealous
God, visiting the iniquity of the
fathers upon the children, unto the
third and fourth generation of them that
hate me, and showing mercy unto
thousands of them that love me, and keep
my commandments. Thou shalt not take the
name of the Lord thy God in vain, for
the Lord will not hold him guiltless
that taketh his name in vain. Remember
the Sabbath day, to keep it holy. Six
days shalt thou labor and do all thy
work. But the seventh day is the Sabbath
of the Lord thy God. In it thou shalt
not do any work. Thou nor thy son, nor
thy daughter, thy man's servant, nor thy
maidervant, nor thy cattle, nor thy
stranger that is within thy gates. For
in six days the Lord made heaven and
earth, the sea, and all that in them is,
and rested the seventh day. Wherefore
the Lord blessed the Sabbath day, and
hollowed it. Honor thy father and thy
mother, that thy days may be long upon
the land which the Lord thy God giveth
thee. Thou shalt not kill. Thou shalt
not commit adultery. Thou shalt not
steal. Thou shalt not bear false witness
against thy neighbor. Thou shalt not
cover thy neighbor's house. Thou shalt
not cover thy neighbor's wife, nor his
man's servant, nor his maid servant, nor
his ox, nor his ass, nor anything that
is thy neighbors.
Thank you for that, brother. Now, let's
turn to Ecclesiastes chapter 12. We just
read the commandments. So let's see
what's the whole duty of mankind.
Ecclesiastes chapter 12. We're going to
pick it up at just two verses. Verse 13
and 14. Go ahead, bro. Let us hear the
conclusion of the whole matter. Fear God
and keep his commandments. For this is
the whole duty of man.
>> For God shall bring every work into
judgment with every secret thing,
whether it be good or whether it be
evil. Right. All right. Now, turn to
Revelation chapter 22. Just read what
our job is. So, if you complete that job
and successful with it, let's see what
rewards you get from it. Revelation
chapter 22. And I just want verse 14 and
15. Go ahead, bro.
Blessed are they that do his
commandments, that they may have right
to the tree of life, and may enter in
through the gates into the city. But
without are dogs and sorcerers and
whoreongers and murderers and idoltors
and whosoever love it and make it a lie.
>> So that's the reading of the law. And as
I said before, we read that every
Saturday before we open up with our
lesson. Um kids, you can go ahead and be
dismissed to children's class.
And my name is Brother Dylan for those
of y'all that don't know. Um, and
reading for me today is brother Demani.
And I want to welcome everybody to the
Israel of God where we teach the Bible
by subject and by title. And today's
title is adversity builds character if
you let it. A couple of weeks ago, I
taught this lesson on sound doctrine if
if you're familiar with that platform.
And I posed a few questions at the
beginning of the lesson, and I'm gonna
pose those same questions to you. So, if
you got laid off from your job while the
rent was due, how would you respond to
that situation?
You feel hopeless or would you lean on
God? When you and your spouse can't seem
to get on the same page and it starts
affecting the household, what do you do?
Do you become bitter toward one another
or do you pray for one another? What if
God allowed your health to fail and you
became physically limited for a season
or even multiple seasons? Would you stop
following him or would you continue
seeking his word even more diligently?
These are common life circumstances that
many people go through. And all this can
be summed up into one word, adversity.
And adversity has a funny way of
revealing who we are under pressure.
Because who you are under pressure says
a lot about your character. Anyone can
appear patient, faithful, and composed.
When life is peaceful, everything is all
good, right? But adversity tests whether
those qualities remain when life
chaotic, painful, unpredictable, and
just plain hard. Some people fold under
pressure by becoming bitter, impatient,
and fearful. Some go as far as to turn
away from God completely. I'm sure we've
all seen that happen.
But when adversity is faced with faith,
it can actually refine, strengthen, and
mature a person spiritually. So this
lesson is not just about going through
hard times. It's about how we respond
when those hard times come. Adversity
can either make you bitter or make you
better, make you weaker or stronger. It
can make you closer to God or push you
away from him. So with that with that
being said, we're going to open up with
Ecclesiastes chapter 3.
We all know what it's like to have a
season of good times, a season of
abundance. everything is is good and
peaceful, right? But we're going to get
ready to read that everything in life
comes and goes. It happens in the season
and that's part of the human experience.
So, we're going to pick it up at
Ecclesiastes chapter 3. I want you to
pick it up at verse one. We're going to
read 1-9.
Go ahead.
>> To everything there is a season and a
time to every purpose under the heaven.
>> So, everything has a season and every
season has a purpose. the reason behind
it. Go ahead.
>> A time to be born and a time to die. A
time to plant and a time to pluck up
that which is planted.
>> So it's a time for life and it's a time
for death. Keep reading.
>> A time to kill and a time to heal. A
time to break down and a time to build
up.
>> So just as well as you can have healing,
you can also have a a season where it
could be some killing going on. Right.
Keep reading.
>> A time to weep and a time to laugh. A
time to mourn and a time to dance.
>> So there's a time for sorrow and there's
a time for joy. You reading?
>> A time to cast away stones and a time to
gather stones together.
>> A time to embrace and a time to refrain
from embracing.
>> There's a time where you going to have a
lot of company people together. Then
there's going to be a time for solitude.
And I'm pretty sure we remember when CO
happened. That was a a very important
time of solitude, right? So keep
reading. A time to get and a time to
lose. A time to keep and a time to cast
the weight.
>> It's a time to increase and it's a time
to decrease. You read
>> a time to rent and a time to sow. A time
to keep silence and a time to speak.
>> Yes. And we know on the Sabbath day,
it's a time to let your words be few.
Right. So, we just seeing here that it's
a time for everything under the sun. Go
ahead.
>> A time to love and a time to hate. A
time of war and a time of peace. You can
actually end at verse eight. So the
human experience consists of good and
bad moments. Everything comes in seasons
and every season has its purpose. So I
want to go to Job. Let's go look at
Job's story and let's see how he handled
his season of adversity, his his se his
low season. Now what I want you to do
while we reading this is put yourself in
his shoes. What would you do if you was
on a a high? The Lord had you protected.
Everything that you wanted, you had. You
was in a good a good space. But what if
you took a lot took it all away? How
would you respond to that? Job chapter
1, I want verse uh pick it up at verse
one. Go ahead.
>> There was a man in the land of Oz whose
name was Job. And that man was perfect
and upright.
>> So we already see he got a good resume
right now. Perfect and upright. Go
ahead. and one that feared God and
assued evil.
>> And there were born unto him seven sons
and three daughters.
>> He was blessed with 10 kids. Keep going.
>> His substance also was 7,000 sheep and
3,000 camels and 500 yogin and 500 shies
and a very great household. So that this
man was the greatest of all the men of
the east.
>> And you know during that time if you had
a lot of um animals and things like
that, you was considered a wealthy
person. And Job would be what you would
consider now as a high value man. All
right. So let's skip to verse six.
Go ahead.
>> Now there was a day when the sons of God
came to present themselves before the
Lord. And Satan came also among them.
>> Okay, let's see what's about to happen.
Keep reading.
>> And the Lord said unto Satan, "Whence
comest thou?" Then Satan answered the
Lord and said, "From going to and fro in
the earth, and from walking up and down
in it." Now, Satan, we all know how
Satan operate. He looking for somebody
to destroy. He looking for some drama.
He looking for to get somebody cut off.
But what did what did God say after
Satan said that? Go ahead.
>> And the Lord said unto Satan, "Has thou
considered my servant Job?"
>> So, he gave Job's name as a test. It's
like Satan saying, "Look, I'm I'm
looking for trouble. Have you considered
my ser my servant Job?" Okay, keep
reading. that there is none like him in
the earth, a perfect and an upright man,
one that feared God and is evil.
>> That's a good account for God to say
that about you, for God to call you
perfect and upright. Keep reading.
>> Then Satan answered the Lord and said,
"Do Job fear God for not?"
>> Oh, does Job does he fear you for no
reason? Let's see why he said that.
Verse 10. Hast not thou made an hedge
about him, and about his house, and
about all that he had on every side?
Thou has blessed the work of his hands,
and his substance is increased in the
land.
>> Keep reading verse 11.
>> But put forth thine hand now, and touch
all that he had, and he will curse thee
to thy face.
>> You gave him everything he want, Lord.
You You got him in a good spot. He He
protected. I can't touch him. Take away
what he got. Take his possessions away.
He going to curse you to your face. put
him through some adversity, he's going
to fall under pressure.
The Lord and Satan could be having that
same conversation about you. You think
about what you going through, maybe the
Lord putting you to a test just like
Job. Keep that in mind. Verse 12. And
the Lord said unto Satan, "Behold, all
that he had is in thy power. Only upon
himself, put not forth thine hand." So
Satan went forth from the presence of
the Lord.
>> All right. So let's keep let's see what
happened. Now the hedge is removed
around Job. Verse 13.
>> And there was a day when his sons and
his daughters were eating and drinking
wine in their elder in the in their
eldest brother's house.
>> Mhm.
>> And there came a messenger unto Job and
said, "The oxen were plowing, and the
asses feeding beside them, and the
Sabians fell upon them, and took them
away. Yeah, they have slain the servants
with the edge of the sword, and I only
am escaped alone to tell thee.
>> So that's problem number one. The oxen,
you know, your your your oxen and your
asses got taken away, and they killed
your servants. Problem number one. All
right, keep reading.
>> While he was yet speaking, there came
also another and said, "The fire of God
has fallen from heaven and had burned up
the sheep and the servants and consumed
them. and I only and I only am escaped
alone to tell thee.
>> Problem number two, in the middle of
that sentence, somebody else coming to
him saying, "The fire from God has
fallen from heaven and burned up the
sheep and killed the servants." So, we
see Job is his his value is here and
he's just losing. He's just losing
money, losing possessions. All right,
keep reading 17. While he was yet
speaking, there came also another and
said, "The Chaldanss made out three
bands and fell upon the camels and have
carried them away. Yet, and have slain
the servants with the edge of the sword,
and I only am escaped alone to tell
thee."
>> Like problem after problem after
problem. Just imagine, you already got
your rent due, now your check short, now
your car break down,
>> then your your kids ain't acting right.
So just put it in that perspective. What
would you do if you got all that
pressure on you? Then people talking
about you at work like it just don't
stop. Then you try to go home and and
get some peace and you drop your keys
when you try to, you know, open the
door. Seem like that be the that be like
the icing on top of the cake and them
keys dropping.
Keep reading, bro. While he was yet
speaking, there came also another and
said, "Thy sons and thy daughters were
eating and drinking wine in their eldest
brother's house.
>> And behold, there came a great wind from
the wilderness, and smoked the four
corners of the house, and it fell upon
the young men, and they are dead. And I
only am escaped alone to tell thee."
>> So now your kids are dead, and this is
happening back to back. one thing right
after the next. But let's see how Job
handles this. Cuz what would you do if
your season changed suddenly? If you
went from a season of joy to a season of
sorrow. If you went from a season of
life to death, what would you do? Let's
see what Job did. Go ahead.
>> Then Job arose and rent his mantle and
shaved his head and fell down upon the
ground and worshiped.
>> So in the midst of his adversity, he
worshiped the Lord. Go ahead. and said,
"Naked came I out of my mother's womb,
and naked shall I return thither. The
Lord gave, and the Lord had taken away.
Blessed be the name of the Lord."
>> So, he praised the Lord in the midst of
all that affliction. He had enough
understanding and enough faith to to
stop in the midst of that and praise the
Lord. Keep reading verse 21.
>> And all this Job sent not nor charged
God foolishly. So he passed the test.
Guess what? Sometimes that adversity can
intensify. You may win one battle. What
if it's what if it's it's part of a long
war, right? Because it's going to get
it's going to get worse, right? So we
see that Job don't care too much about
his possessions to where he he just
forsake the Lord. Let's go to Job
chapter 2.
>> Pick it up at verse one.
>> Go ahead. Again, there was a day when
the sons of God came to present
themselves before the Lord. And Satan
came also among them to present himself
before the Lord. And the Lord said unto
Satan, From whence comest thou? And
Satan answered the Lord, and said, From
going to and fro in the earth, and from
walking up and down in it.
>> Verse three. And the Lord said unto
Satan, "Hast thou considered my servant
Job, that there is none like him in the
earth, a perfect and an upright man, one
that fearth God and Yeshua evil." And
still he holdeth fast his integrity,
although thou movest me against him to
destroy him without cause.
>> The things that was happening in Job was
pretty much without probable cause. He
didn't do no sin. He didn't do nothing
wrong. So, he just getting punished just
because of a conversation that the Lord
and Satan had just because the Lord is
putting Job on a on a on a um chopping
block just saying how he going to handle
it. Basically, the Lord is bragging on
Job. He perfect and upright. You might
try to break him, but he ain't going to
fall. Let's keep reading.
Verse four. And Satan answered to the
Lord and said, "Skin for skin." Yeah.
All that a man had will he give for his
life. But put forth thine hand now, and
touch his bone and his flesh, and he
will curse thee to thy face.
>> Yeah. Anybody serve you as long as you
don't take their life from them, as long
as you don't hurt them, you can take
their possessions all day. But put some
affliction on his body. Let's see what
Let's see how he handles that. Verse
six. And the Lord said unto Satan,
"Behold, he is in thine hand, but save
his life."
>> All right, keep reading.
>> So went Satan forge from the presence of
the Lord and smoke Job with sore boils
from the sole of his foot unto his
crown.
>> So he obviously got to have some type of
sickness. And if you read through Job
through the entire book of Job, you'll
see that he done lost weight. Like
people can't even recognize him when
they see him. So he got some type of
sickness on him that lasted for a long
time. So this a real it's a real issue
that he dealing with. Verse eight.
>> And he took him a potter to scrape
himself with all and he sat down among
the ashes.
>> And let's see in the midst of his
adversity, right? In the midst of him
having losing his possessions and his
his flesh is being afflicted, sometimes
other people can come in your come in
your life and try to give you some
advice and make it worse or it can
provoke you to do the wrong thing. But
how do you how do you handle that
situation? Keep reading verse N.
>> Then said his wife unto him, does thou
still retain thine integrity? Curse God
and die.
>> That's your response to a perfect and
upright man. and and you his wife, you
must hate him or something. You tell him
to curse God and die. I don't know.
Let's finish verse 10.
>> But he said unto her, "Thou speakest as
one of the foolish woman speaking."
>> And you know how ears work to talk.
Woman, you talking crazy.
He read
>> what shall we receive good at the hand
of God, and shall we not receive evil?
In all this did not Job sin with his
lips. So my question again as we reading
this, yes, Job is passing the test, but
what about you? What is your affliction
that the Lord is putting you through,
right? And like I said, if your season
of suffering intensifies,
you have a certain level where if it get
past that level, you going you going to
sin against the Lord, you going to curse
him, you going to become bitter, you
going to fold under pressure, or you
going to stay fold on to your faith.
Now, let's go to Job chapter 7 because
like I said, this thing was lasting with
Job pretty long. Wasn't a short
affliction that he dealt with, right?
And it was even people looking at him a
certain way. People didn't respect him
the same as they would just because he
was being afflicted,
Job chapter 7,
and let's look at how his talk is now.
Now, he's not cursing the Lord, but it
seems like from this his talk is like
he's confused about what's going on.
Like, why am I going through this? I
didn't sin. What's going on, Lord? Job
chapter 7, pick it up at verse one.
Go ahead. Is there not an appointed time
to man upon earth? Are not his days also
like the days of an hierling? Mhm.
>> As a servant earnestly desired the
shadow and as an hierling lookth for
look look itth for the reward of his
work.
>> So all he's saying is that just like a a
servant working in the hot sun is
waiting to get relief from the shadows
right from some shade. And as a hirling
a worker just doing some some type of
menial work some type of hard labor and
he's just waiting to get paid. That's
the reward. Verse three. So am I made to
possess months of vanity and weary some
nights are appointed un are appointed to
me.
>> So I'm waiting months to get some relief
for this thing. This thing this this
thing have been going on for months. We
you know what I'm saying? And it says
where of some nights are appointed to
me. He can't even sleep. So we see
obviously this affliction has got to
him. He read when I lie down I see when
shall I arise and the night be gone? And
I am full of tossins to and fro unto the
dawning of the day.
>> And sometimes you can be so stressed out
to where you can't sleep at night. You
know it happens. Verse five.
>> My flesh is clothed with worms and
clouds of dust. My skin is broken and
become loathome.
>> Flesh is clothed with worms and claws of
dust. My skin is broken. It's almost
like he describing like he's he homeless
or something. So he Job ain't doing too
good. Verse six,
>> my days are swifter than a weaver's
shuttle and are spent without hope.
>> So see now this is that hopeless talk.
This ain't this ain't the same talk that
he was talking at first. So we see now
he going through it a little bit. His
mindset changed. He a little bit
emotional. So he's he's feeling
hopeless. Verse seven.
>> Oh remember that my life is wind. Mine
eyes shall no more see good.
>> So he feel like my life is over. I
can't. This is it. This is the end of
me, right? Skip to verse 11.
>> Therefore, I will not refrain my mouth.
I will speak in the anguish of my
spirit. I will complain in the
bitterness of my soul. Sometimes that
complaining can make your make your
outlook on your adversity or your
hardship even worse. So, you got to
that's one of them moments you got to
talk to yourself or talk talk out of
that negative self-t talk. All right,
let's go to Job chapter 10.
Because we understand the conversation
that L the Lord had with Satan. Job
don't understand that in this moment.
And sometimes because we don't
understand why something is happening to
us, we tend to lean on our own
understanding.
All right. Look, we got to start back.
Please ask chapter 3.
Matter of fact, let's start with the
law. Go to Exodus 20.
All right, we're gonna pick it up at Job
chapter 10. Uh, give me verse one. Go
ahead.
>> My soul is weary of my life. I will
leave my complaint on upon myself. I
will speak in the bitterness of my soul.
>> Yeah, Job is he he has that bitter
attitude right now. He's complaining.
Verse two,
>> I will say unto God, do not condemn me.
Show me wherefore thou contendest with
me.
>> Why, God? Why? Why are you fighting with
me? Why me? Don't we we tend to have
some them talks like that? So we
questioning the Lord like what have I
done? Why me? Why I'm going through
this? Verse three.
>> Is it good unto thee that thou shouldest
oppress that thou shouldest despise the
work of thine hands and shine upon the
counsel of the wicked?
>> So he thinking as the Lord hate him. But
us looking from the outside looking in,
we understand that the Lord can afflict
you and still show you love, right? We
understand that the Lord can test you
and still build you up through those uh
through those tests. Now let's skip
verse six.
>> That thou inquireest after mine iniquity
and searchest after my sin.
>> Verse seven.
>> Thou knowest that I am not wicked and
there is none that can deliver out of
thine hand.
>> Right? Job didn't do any sin. The Lord
called him himself perfect and upright.
So, but what about you? What if you
don't understand the purpose of your
affliction?
Let's go to Ecclesiastes chapter 1.
You know, we got to see ourselves in
this book. You may read about Job and
his affliction, but like I said, what if
you was in that situation?
So, if you don't understand your
affliction or you don't understand what
you're going through, you got to get in
this book to find that understanding.
Ecclesiastes chapter 1 verse 13. Go
ahead.
and I gave my heart to seek and search
out by wisdom concerning all things that
are done under heaven.
>> Right? So Solomon is saying right here
that he put his mind to just seek and
cir out search out everything that
happens under the sun, good, bad, ugly,
even adversity. Keep reading.
>> This sore travail had God given to the
sons of man to be exercised therewith.
So God gave us the wherewithal to be
able to search out things concerning the
human experience. One of those things
that we talk about today is adversity.
So we going we going to do a deep dive
into this thing. Go to Genesis chapter
1. We going to see why does life have to
be hard? Why do we have to go through
adversity in the first place?
I'm going to tell y'all we could have
had a soft life.
Genesis chapter 1 and I just want verse
27 and 28.
Y'all some time to turn. They told me
last time I was moving too fast.
All right. Genesis chapter 1, give me
verse 27 through 28. Go ahead.
>> So God created man in his own image. In
the image of God created he him. male
and female created he them.
>> And God blessed them. And God said unto
them, "Be fruitful and multiply, and
replenish the earth, and subdue it, and
have dominion over the fish of the sea,
and over the fowl of the air, and over
every living thing that moveth upon the
earth."
>> So he told them from the get-go, have
some babies. And right here, it wasn't
no it wasn't no um hardship, right?
wasn't no adversity, no challenges with
being fruitful and multiply. Verse 31.
>> And God saw everything that he had made.
And behold, it was very good. And the
evening and the morning were the six
days.
>> So no bad, nothing bad. Everything was
good. Right? This was a soft life so
far. Go to Genesis chapter 2.
Pick it up at verse 8. Then we're going
to skip. Go ahead. And the Lord God
planted a garden eastward in Eden, and
there he put the man whom he had formed.
>> So the Lord God planted a garden in Eden
and put Adam in there. Skip down to
verse 15. Go ahead.
>> And the Lord God took the man and put
him into the Garden of Eden to dress it
and to keep it.
>> So man had a job at this point, but
again wasn't no hardship associate
associated with labor. He had a job. He
had a responsibility. He read, "And the
Lord God commanded the man, saying, of
every tree of the garden, thou mayest
freely eat."
>> So he could have freely ate from from
the ground, no problems.
Verse 17,
>> "But of the tree of the knowledge of
good and evil, thou shalt not eat of it.
For in the day that thou eatest thereof,
thou shalt surely die."
>> He just had one commandment. Just don't
eat of the tree of the knowledge of good
and evil. Don't take no knowledge from
Satan. That's it. You could eat from
every tree, even the tree of life. But
we see, you know, man, we know the
story. Man didn't listen. Go to Genesis
chapter 3. So, we know Satan rolled up
on Eve, slick talk her into the, you
know, um, eating of that tree. She
brought that same knowledge to her
husband. We're going to pick it up at
verse eight. Go ahead.
And they heard the voice of the Lord
walking in the garden in the in the cool
of the deep. And Adam and his wife hid
themselves from the presence of the Lord
God amongst the trees of the garden.
>> Now it wasn't none of that when we read
in Genesis 1 and two. So now they hiding
from the Lord. Go ahead.
>> And the Lord God called unto Adam and
said unto him, "Where art thou?" And he
said, "I heard thy voice in the garden,
and I was afraid because I was naked,
and I hid myself." This next verse I
always think is so cold because it's
like from a parent your kid do something
and you like you know the perfect
question to ask him to catch him in the
act.
>> You know exactly what to ask. That's why
I think this verse 11 was so cold. Go
ahead and read it.
>> And he said who told thee that thou was
naked? Hast thou eaten of the tree
whereof I commanded thee that thou
shouldest not eat?
>> Yeah they they saying. But let's see
what Adam said. Verse 12. And the man
said, "The woman whom thou gavest to be
with me, she gave me of the tree, and I
did eat."
>> Just like one sibling blamed the other
sibling, but both of y'all in trouble,
but you going to put the blame on the
other sibling. Keep reading.
>> And the Lord God said unto the woman,
"What is this that thou has done?" And
the woman said, "The servant begile me,
and I did eat."
>> Right? Now, let's skip to verse 16. So,
let's see what comes as a consequence.
For both parties sinned, Adam and Eve,
right? We're going to look at the woman.
Verse 16.
>> Unto the woman, he said, I will greatly
multiply thy sorrow and thy conception.
>> Uhoh.
>> In sorrow thou shalt bring forth
children, and thy desire shall be to thy
husband, and he shall rule over thee.
>> But correct me if I'm wrong. Right. When
we read in Genesis chapter 1, he told
him, "Be fruitful and multiply." But it
wasn't no sorrow with it. It was
supposed to be something that was easy,
something that was, you know, not a
headache. But for all my sister that had
kids that have kids of giving birth,
they'll tell you it's a beautiful thing,
right? I have four kids and I've seen my
wife give birth four times. I don't see
nothing beautiful about that delivery
room.
>> It's not. Now, after the fact, yeah, but
during, no, I see sorrow. I see pain. I
see a whole lot of stuff.
>> So,
That's some adversity right there.
>> And even with raising your kids, you go
through some adversity cuz you got to
protect them from the world out there.
So they had a soft life. Verse 17, let's
let's get to the brothers. And unto Adam
he said, because thou has he argued unto
the voice of thy wife, and has eaten of
the tree of which I commanded thee,
saying, Thou shalt not eat of it, cursed
is the ground for thy sake. and sorrow
shalt thou eat of it all the days of thy
life.
>> See why he said that? Verse 18.
>> Thorns also and thistles shall it bring
forth to thee, and thou shalt eat the
herb of the field.
>> Now, he told him to dress and keep the
garden at first, right? Wasn't no no no
no difficulties with that. Now, he's
saying it's going to be thorns and
thistles in your labor. So, brothers,
when you got to get up in the morning
and go to work and barely had enough
sleep, thank Adam for that. That's why
you got to go through that adversity
because of that sin. 19
>> In the sweat of thy face shalt thou eat
bread till thou return unto the ground
for out of it was thou taken for dust
thou art and unto dust shalt thou
return.
>> So childbearing came with no adversity
and work came with no adversity. But it
was sin that brought that hardship.
Right now let's skip. It was some it's
something else though that we could have
gotten freely. Verse 22, skip to 22. Go
ahead and read. And the Lord God said,
"Behold, the man has become as one of us
to know good and evil. And now, lest he
put forth his hand and take also of the
tree of life and eat and live forever."
>> Therefore the Lord God sent him forth
from the Garden of Eden to till the
ground from whence he was taken.
>> When he told Adam he could eat freely,
right, from the garden, that didn't just
include eating from the ground, that
also included eating from the tree of
life. Now, we got to work for our
salvation. We got to go the long way
around to get that crown of glory. We
could have just freely ate from the Lord
right then and there.
That's why when you open your Bible and
you reading something, you you got to
chat GPT it, get your dictionary up, go
call your brothers and sisters, watch a
lesson. It ain't have to be like that,
but thanks to Adam, we it is that that's
how it is.
Let's finish there. Verse 24. So he
drove out the man and he placed at the
east of the garden of Eden cherubims and
a flaming sword which turned every way
to keep the way of the tree of life. So
now we understand why life is hard. We
understand where that hardship comes
from. So we just can look at affliction
as it's a part of the human experience.
People live, people die, people get
rich, people go broke. It happens. Go to
Romans chapter 3.
really make you feel some type of way
when you realize that like how easy we
could have had it. And like I know
people we typically tend to look at
Israel, right, during black history like
how we could have been different as a
nation, but just in general as a as the
human race, we could have just been
different had we not sinned.
Romans chapter 3,
pick it up at verse 23. Go ahead.
>> For all have sinned and come short of
the glory of God. So our opportunity to
live a soft life was ruined by sin. So
now we got to get it out the mud. Now we
got to work for everything that we got.
>> So and we know sinners got to suffer,
right? Like we know it's okay. Yeah. If
you sin, just stop sinning. We
understand that. But sometimes we forget
that the righteous have to do a lot of
suffering as well. Even more so than
probably than sinners. At least for
right now.
>> First Peter chapter 4.
1 Peter chapter 4.
You want two verses out of here. I want
verse 14. No, 15. 1 Peter chapter 4.
Give me verse 15 and 16. Go ahead.
But let none of you suffer as a murderer
or as a thief or as an evildoer or as an
busy body in other men's matters. So
don't sin. Cuz if you suffering and you
sinning, well, just stop sinning. Keep
the commandments, right? Cuz you just
getting the punishment that you deserve.
But what if I'm righteous? What if I got
a a resume like Job? Verse 16.
>> Yet if any man suffer as a Christian,
let him not be ashamed.
>> Don't be ashamed. Go ahead.
>> But let him glorify God on this behalf.
>> So I went here just to show you that
it's acceptable. It's acceptable to God
for us to suffer for righteousness as
opposed to wickedness. But what is the
right way to suffer though? How are we
supposed to take that suffering? Let's
go to our next spot. Let's go to
Philippians chapter 4. I want to show
you how you should respond to those
difficult situations. See, now we're not
ignorant about adversity. We understand
why why it's in the world now. We
understand why we got to go through hard
times. But now that we know that we got
to go through them, how should we handle
it?
Philippians chapter 4,
we're going to pick it up at verse 11
through13.
Go ahead.
>> Not that I speak in respect of want, for
I have learned in whatsoever state I am,
therewith to be content.
>> So, be content in whatever state. Let's
see what he's talking about. 12.
>> I know both how to be a base.
>> I know how to be low. I know how to
decrease. Go ahead. And I know how to
abound.
>> I know how to increase. I know what it's
like when my tax money hit. And I know
what it's like when I'm when I'm broke.
>> Y'all know how that is.
>> You read.
>> Everywhere and in all things I am
instructed both to be full and to be
hungry,
>> both to abound and to suffer need.
>> So I got to learn how to go have and
have. I got to learn how to have and
have not.
>> Yeah. You got to learn how to suffer.
You got to learn how to endure that. And
this is why it's really it's really, you
know, I know we get emotional about it
and we have our ups and downs and things
like that, but read verse 13.
>> I can do all things through Christ which
strengthenth me.
>> Once you understand that the source of
your strength is Jesus, you can get
through whatever that that low season
is. Just like he gets you through your
se your high season, you can get get you
through your low seasons. So, you got to
keep that at the forefront of your mind
when you're going through your
affliction. Let's go to Isaiah chapter
54.
Sometimes you just got to just got to
say that I can do all things through
Christ with strengthening me. Like I
always look at like Muhammad Ali. He he
did a lot of talking, but I read
somewhere where he did that to kind of
hype himself up. Sometimes you got to do
the same thing when you're going through
a low moment and your flesh is getting
to you. Just talk to yourself. talk
yourself out of doing something or
saying something or thinking something
crazy. Isaiah chapter 54 and this this
another one of those verses that you
can, you know, recall on when you going
through something just as a reminder.
Isaiah chapter 54, pick it up at verse
11.
So, we're going to see who he's talking
to in this verse. Go ahead.
>> Oh, thou afflicted.
>> So, he's talking to the people that's
going through that adversity. Go ahead.
tossed with tempest and not comforted.
>> So these are people that's going through
a storm. Go ahead.
>> Behold, I will lay thy stones with fair
colors and lay thy foundations with
sapphires.
>> So what is he talking about here? So God
is speaking to those who are afflicted,
battered by life storms, and lacking
comfort.
Now this can make you feel broken. But
he said, "I will lay thy stones with
fair colors and lay thy foundations with
sapphires." He's going to build you a
stronger foundation. That affliction
that you going through, that storm that
you going through, he going to build you
he he's going to use that storm to make
you stronger in that process. That's
what he's saying. Verse 12.
>> And I will make thy windows of a gates
and thy gates of carbunkles and all thy
borders of pleasant stones.
>> Right? So all these are different stones
and jewels that he's referring to things
that's going to make you glorious.
Right? It's not talking physical. It's
just saying that he's going to allow you
to have qualities that will make you a
stronger, a better, more mature
Christian in this walk. 13
>> And all thy children shall be taught of
the Lord, and great shall be the peace
of thy children.
>> Even your children are going to benefit
from that. 14 and righteousness shalt
thou be established. Thou shalt be far
from oppression, for thou shalt not
fear, and from terror, for it shall not
come near.
>> Right? So now read verse 15.
>> Behold, they shall surely gather
together, but not by me. Whosoever shall
gather together against thee shall fall
for thy sake.
>> Seem like the battle already won, right?
>> Seem like it's already it's we already
victorious right now. Verse 16.
Yeah.
>> Behold, I have created the smith.
>> So, that's talking about a blacksmith. A
blacksmith is somebody who a craftsman
who heats shapes and forges metal into
tools, weapons, or any other objects
using fire, a hammer, a hammer, and
anvil. Okay. So, he said, "I created the
blacksmith, right? I created the weapon
or like or basically like he did with
Job. He allowed Satan to put his hands
on Job, right? So the Lord is saying the
same person that that's going to you
afflicting you or these same situations,
he allowed it. So he's not he's not uh
ignorant about what's going on in your
life, he knows exactly what's going on.
You read that bloweth the coals in the
fire and that bringeth forth an
instrument for his work. And I have
created the waster to destroy. Right? So
he created he understands these weapons
that that's that's against you. Right?
Verse 17.
>> No weapon that is formed against thee
shall prosper.
>> So he he's allowing it, but he also
knows that whatever weapon that's formed
against you, it's not going to prosper.
He knows everything about it. He knows
how to cut it off. He knows how to stop
it. Right? But it does say the weapons
are going to form. They're just not
going to prevail over you. So you got to
keep that in mind. Finish that. and
every tongue that shall rise against
thee in judgment, thou shalt condemn.
>> That's right.
>> This is the heritage of the servants of
the Lord, and their righteousness is of
me, sayeth the Lord.
>> So those two verses that you can put
Philippians 4, Isaiah 54, that you can
just use to remind yourself that the
Lord going to get you through it. You
just got to be patient. Now, let's go
look at an example. Let's go to Exodus
chapter 6.
And I want you to I want you to notice a
pattern.
Something happens behind the scenes.
Some adversity kicks in and then the
Lord comes save the day.
Any of y'all that been through some
stuff, you are you you know that
happens. The Lord going to save you
eventually. You just got to get you just
got to be able to look in the midst of
that adversity and just know like, you
know what, it is what it is. I'm going
to get through this season. Exodus
chapter 6.
Going to pick it up at verse 5. Exodus
Verse 5.
And I have also heard the groaning of
the children of Israel whom the
Egyptians keep in bondage. And I have
remembered my covenant.
>> So he's he's talking to Moses. So he
already understand what Israel are going
through at this time because they
slaving they are slaves in Egypt. Go
ahead. Verse six. Wherefore say unto the
children of Israel, I am the Lord, and I
will bring you out from under the
burdens of the Egyptians, and I will rid
you out of their bondage, and I will
redeem you with a stretched out arm, and
with great judgment.
>> So, the battle is already won. Now,
right here, we don't know exactly, well,
we know how the Lord is going to end up
saving the day, but Moses don't
understand what's going on. He just know
the Lord going to save him. He don't
know how. Keep reading. and I will take
you to me for a people, and I will be to
you a God, and you shall know that I am
the Lord your God, which bringeth you
out from under the burdens of the
Egyptians."
>> Verse eight,
>> I will bring you in unto the land,
concerning the which I did swear to give
it to Abraham, to Isaac, and to Jacob,
and I will give it to you for
inheritage. I am the Lord. So the Lord
already gave Moses the game plan way
before the 10 plagues happened way
before he split the sea. The game plan
was already in play. Israel just don't
know about it. They don't know the
details of it. You don't know the
details that God has for whatever you
going through. Right? You just got to
trust that Christ is my strength and no
weapon uh no weapon that forms against
me shall prosper. That's all you need to
tell yourself. You ain't got to know
everything else.
>> Verse nine. And Moses spake so unto the
children of Israel, but they hearkened
not unto Moses for anguish of spirit and
for cruel bondage.
>> They couldn't see the vision because
they so caught up in their affliction.
Oh,
>> they couldn't see what the the Lord is
is here to save you, but you so caught
up. So, you ain't even trying to listen
to what Moses saying. Go to Exodus 14.
Because at this point, Israel has
already been delivered from the
Egyptians. the 10 plagues have happened.
And you would think after these 10
plagues, it shouldn't be no doubt in
their mind that the Lord is who he say
he is. But we know we dealing with a
stiff neck people.
Exodus 14,
going to pick it up at verse one.
Go ahead, bro.
And the Lord spake unto Moses, saying,
"Speak unto the children of Israel, that
they turn and encamp before Pi Haheroth,
between Maggdal and the sea, over
against Beael Zafon, before it shall
encamp by the sea."
>> Now, God is he's about to do his big
finale. Israel still don't know what's
about to happen, but they just following
the Lord's orders. Okay, go ahead. For
Pharaoh will say of the children of
Israel, "They are entangled in the land,
the wilderness had shut them in." And I
will harden Pharaoh's heart, that he
shall follow after them, and I will be
honored upon Pharaoh and upon all his
hosts, that the Egyptians may know that
I am the Lord." And they did so.
>> So the Lord just setting a trap. So when
you think about people coming against
you at work or people talking crazy
about you or afflicting you or trying to
make you sin against God or make you get
out of character, sometimes people do
things for their own hurt. I seen
something that happened at work this
past week or God was doing something
inappropriate or or saying inappropriate
things and he was he was out of there.
He had three occasions that he he did
something inappropriate or said
something that he shouldn't have been
saying to different people and he got
kicked out of there. Now he's not a
problem problem no more at that
establishment. Same thing can happen in
your life. Just got to let the Lord do
his work. Where we at? Verse four.
>> Verse five.
>> Go ahead. Verse five.
>> And it was told the king of Egypt that
the people fled and the heart of Pharaoh
and of his servants was turned against
the people and they said, "Why have we
done this that we have let Israel go
from serving us?"
>> Didn't he say he was going to harden
Pharaoh's heart? So his plan is being is
like all right cool Lord I'm just follow
you everything happening the Lord can't
lie. Verse six.
>> And he made ready his chariot and took
his people with him.
>> Go ahead. Verse. So we see the weapons
forming.
>> The weapons forming right now. Verse
seven.
>> And he took 600 chosen chariots and all
the chariots of Egypt and captains over
every one of them.
>> Now skip to verse 10.
>> And when Pharaoh drew nigh, the children
of Israel lifted up their eyes. And
behold, the Egyptians marched after
them, and they were sore afraid. Oh, my
bad. Go ahead. Finish that.
>> And the children of Israel cried out
unto the Lord.
>> So Israel, they're scared now. They
scared. They see all these Egyptians
with all this this war material and
everything coming at them, right?
They're looking at Egyptians in front of
them and the Red Sea is in to their
backs. So this is an impossible
situation, right? Verse 11. And they
said unto Moses, because there were no
graves in Egypt, hast thou taken us away
to die in the wilderness,
wherefore hast thou dealt dust with us,
to carry us forth out of Egypt.
Sometimes when you going through some
stuff, some people just like they like
to point the finger and blame. Moses was
sent to help y'all. He working on behalf
of the Lord. So now now the 10 plagues
wasn't even enough to show y'all that
the Lord is going to deliver y'all. I
mean, for goodness sakes, he turned the
river to blood. That was the first
plague.
So now you see these Egyptians, y'all
already defeated them. You took their
gold. You left out of their land. So you
see them coming at you now. It's like,
you brought us here to get killed,
>> right? Where's your faith at? You got to
realize who's your strength in that in
that moment.
>> Where we at?
>> Verse 12.
>> Me verse 12. Is not this the word that
we did tell thee in Egypt, saying, "Let
us alone, that we may serve the
Egyptians,
for it had been better for us to serve
the Egyptians," than that we should die
in the wilderness.
>> You going to talk? Think about how much
of a slap in the face that is to the
Lord. I'mma save you from the Egyptians.
Now, it would have been better if we
would have stayed in Egypt. That's a
slave mentality. And you don't want to
be a slave to your afflictions, right?
You just got to know the Lord going to
save you. He gave Moses the game plan.
Moses tried to bring it to Israel. They
couldn't hear because they were so
caught up in what they was going
through. And even now, Moses is still
trying to encourage them. Verse 13. And
Moses said unto the people, "Fear ye
not, stand still, and see the salvation
of the Lord, which he will show to you
today. For the Egyptians whom ye have
seen today, ye shall see them again no
more forever.
>> Moses don't know exactly what's going
on. He don't know. He just know God got
it. He don't know what the Lord about to
do to them.
>> The Lord shall fight for you, and he
shall hold your peace.
>> Just be cool. God got it. Keep reading.
>> And the Lord said unto Moses, wherefore
Christ thou unto me? Speak unto the
children of Israel that they go forward.
>> Moses, stop wasting time. Go for it.
This battle already, it's already over
with. Go for it, Moses. 16
>> But lift thou up thy rod, and stretch
out thine hand over the sea, and divide
it, and the children of Israel shall go
on dry ground through the midst of the
sea.
>> Wait, how that's going to happen, Lord?
You telling me to It's a The water's
right behind me. You want me to just
walk in the water and drown? Let's skip.
Go to verse 21.
And Moses stretched out his hand over
the sea. And the Lord caused the sea to
go back by a strong east wind all that
night and made the sea dry land and the
waters were divided.
>> Who would have known the Lord would have
did that? Who would have known? So think
about it when you going through some
financial problems and you get some
money in your account and you don't know
where it came from. It could have been
from something that happened some years
ago, a car accident. I don't know.
Whatever it was, but that money in your
account, you ain't stole it. Hopefully,
you didn't steal it, but we see the Lord
put it in there.
>> Or you sick. You've been dealing with a
sickness and then the Lord just all of a
sudden you just up and you you good now.
It can happen that way.
Keep reading.
>> Your spot.
>> Yes.
>> Supposed to keep me on track, bro.
>> I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
Verse uh
>> 17
no 22
>> 22.
>> And the children of Israel went into the
midst of the sea upon the dry ground,
and the waters were a wall unto them on
their right hand and on their left.
>> That's right. Keep reading.
>> And the Egyptians pursued and went in
after them to the midst of the sea, even
all Pharaoh's horses, his chariots, and
his horsemen.
>> They don't even know what they getting
themselves into right now. 24
>> And it came to pass that in the morning
watch, the Lord looked unto the host of
the Egyptians through the pillar of fire
and of the cloud, and troubled the host
of the Egyptians.
>> 25 and took off their chariot wheels,
that they drave them heavily, so that
the Egyptians said, "Let us flee from
the face of Israel, for the Lord fighted
for them against the Egyptians."
>> No weapon that forms against you will
prosper. They they had everything in
their mind to go and kill uh kill
Israel, go doing some harm, but they
didn't understand that the Lord was
fighting for them. And once they
recognized it, it's too late. You read,
"And the Lord said unto Moses, stretch
out thine hand over the sea, that the
waters may come again upon the
Egyptians, upon their chariots, and upon
their horsemen." And Moses stretched
forth his hand over the sea. And the sea
returned to its strength when the
morning appeared. Mhm.
>> And the Egyptians fled against it. And
the Lord overthrew the Egyptians in the
midst of the sea.
>> But the Lord had already told them what
was going to happen. So this it
shouldn't even be no surprise. Like, oh,
see the Egyptians. Okay. Well, I don't
know what y'all plan on doing, but God
got us over here, right? So, it's just
it's just things that you got like I say
it all the time. People complain about
bills, but what are bills to a Red Sea?
I don't even know what that's like to
see a a a walk in the ocean and see a
wall of water to my left and to my right
and it just walk through. We all know
what bill problems look like, but that's
small compared to this happening right
here. That's what you call a miracle.
So, if the Lord can make that a miracle,
what's putting a few extra dollars in
your pocket? It's nothing. It all belong
to him anyway.
>> Keep reading. And the waters returned
and covered the chariots and the
horsemen and all the host of Pharaoh
that came into the sea after them. There
remained not so much as one of them.
>> Didn't Moses tell them they was not
going to see the Egyptians no more?
>> Problem solved. Uh where we at? 28. Skip
to verse 31.
>> And Israel saw that great work which the
Lord did upon the Egyptians.
>> But that wasn't the first great work he
did. He already completed the 10
plagues. He already delivered y'all from
Egypt and took a nation of slaves, made
them rich because y'all had y'all had
the riches of the Egyptians. So that
wasn't the first time he did it. Keep
reading.
>> And the people feared the Lord and
believed the Lord and his servant Moses.
>> So finally now they want to believe. But
we know Israel, they faith go up and
down, up and down. So Moses responded to
the sight of the Egyptians with faith.
Israel responded with doubt. So if if
God already gave them the victory but
they doubted, what does this say about
their faith? Ask yourself that same
question. If you got scriptures that you
can recall on Philippians chapter 4,
Isaiah chapter 54, whatever scriptures
that you use to to you know motivate
yourself, if you can read those and call
on, but you still doubt, what does that
say about your character? What does that
say about the type of Christian you are?
Go to Proverbs 24.
That's why you got to be real careful
with that negative self-t talk when you
going through something cuz that's
revealing your true character. It's easy
to be a Christian when life is good. But
let let some hardships start coming. Let
you start losing some sleep. Let you
start your bank account start dipping.
Let you start having people irritate you
at work. Then that's when you really got
to show forth them fruits of the spirit
that longsuffering. And it just occurred
to me this week like longsuffering
literally means to suffer for a long
time.
>> I don't know why that just stuck out to
me like this week, but that's what it
is. Just suffering for a long time.
Proverbs chapter 24 verse 10. Go ahead.
>> If thou faint in the day of adversity,
thy strength is small. So if you going
through something and you being you
bitter, you complaining, you losing your
faith, says your strength is small. But
hold on, we read in Philippians chapter
4 that the Christ is the source of your
strength. Does that mean he's not
strong? No. What that means is you're
diminishing his strength because if you
don't have faith, then Christ can't do
the work for you. You got to believe
first. So that's how you get that
strength. That strength, you have to
believe. But if you faint in the day of
adversity, your strength is small. But
look at another example. 1st Samuel
chapter 9.
So we not just I'm not just pointing out
these verses just because just just
because these are things that I actually
believe. These are things that you have
to believe as well.
Because if you don't truly believe this
book, then I mean, what's going to be
the solution to your problems?
1 Samuel chapter 9, want a couple of
verses out of here.
Give me verse 15 through
17.
Once you get there, bro, go ahead and
read.
Now the Lord had told Samuel in his ear
a day before Saul came, saying,
"Tomorrow, about this time, I will send
thee a man out of the land of Benjamin.
Thou shalt anoint him to be captain over
my people Israel, that he may save my
people out of the hand of the
Philistines. For I have for I have
looked upon my people, because their cry
is come unto me."
>> Now, when we read in in Exodus, we saw
the conversation behind the scenes,
right? We knew what the adversity was
and we saw the outcome. No different.
This is the conversation between the
Lord and Samuel.
I'm you. I want you to anoint Saul to be
captain over my people Israel and he's
going to save them from the Philistines.
Battle already won. That's the whole
reason Saul was set up as king. Right.
Where we at?
>> Verse 17.
>> Verse 17. Go ahead. And when Samuel saw
Saul, the Lord said unto him, behold the
man whom I spake to thee of this same
shall reign over my people.
>> So we see right now the Lord already his
game plan is not hidden. It's already is
already known. Now let's skip to 1st
Samuel chapter 10
verse 1-10.
Go ahead. Then Samuel took a vial of oil
and poured it upon his head and kissed
him and said, "Is it not because the
Lord had anointed thee to be captain
over his inheritance?"
>> That's right. Keep going. Verse two.
>> "When thou art departed from me today,
then thou shalt find two men by Rachel
Sepiler in the border of Benjamin at
Zela. And they will say unto thee, the
asses which thou wentest to seek are
found, and lo, thy father had left the
care of the asses, and sorrowed for you,
saying, "What shall I do for my son?"
>> So, it's it's basically four prophecies
that the uh the Lord is telling him
what's going to happen. All right, this
is the first one. Okay,
let's go read the second one. Verse
three. Then shalt thou go on forward
from then, and thou shalt come to the
plain of Taber, and there shall meet
thee three men going up to God to Bethl,
one carrying three kids, and another
carrying three loaves of bread, and
another carrying a bottle of wine.
>> Verse four,
>> and they will salute thee, and give thee
two loaves of bread, which thou shalt
receive of their hands. All right. So,
this is this is the second prophecy that
that's going to come to come to pass.
Verse five.
>> After that, thou shalt come to the hill
of God, where is the garrison of the
Philistines. And it shall come to pass
when thou art come thither to the city
that thou shalt meet a company of
prophets coming down from the high place
with the sulttery and a tab and a pipe
and a harp before them, and they shall
prophesy. You read in verse six,
>> and the spirit of the Lord will come
upon thee, and thou shalt pro prophesy
with them, and shall be turned into
another man.
>> So pretty much the Lord has just given
Saul a set of directions to carry out.
Nothing crazy, right? Now, let's see if
Read verse eight.
>> Verse seven.
>> Yeah, go ahead. Verse seven.
>> And let it be when these signs are come
unto thee, that thou do as occasion
serve thee, for God is with thee. He
didn't say if these signs come unto
thee. He said when these signs come to
thee. All right. Verse eight.
>> And thou shalt go down before me to
Gilgal. And behold, I will come down
unto thee to offer burnt offerings and
and to sacrifice sacrifices of peace
offerings. Seven days shalt thou tar
till I come to thee and show thee what
thou shalt do.
>> Keep verse eight in mind because that's
the one that we going we going to look
deeper into. Okay. Verse eight. Well,
look at verse N.
>> And it was so that when he had turned
his back to go from Samuel, God gave him
another heart, and all those signs came
to pass that day.
>> So those first three that we read about
came to pass. The plan happened exactly
how the Lord directed it. All right? So
if the Lord can show you in these
different ways that he's with you, he's
got you every step of the way, then why
is it when you get a certain type of
affliction that fold and you start to
doubt? He done led him through all those
other three, but there this in verse
eight, Saul is unfold under pressure. So
read verse eight again. Go ahead. And
thou shalt go down before me to Gilgal,
and behold, I will come down unto thee
to offer burnt offerings, and to
sacrifice sacrifices of peace offerings.
>> So I want you to go down to Gilgal. And
Samuel was saying, I will come down to
thee to offer burnt offerings and and
make sacrifices. Okay, read.
>> Seven days shalt thou tar till I come to
thee.
>> So you going to wait on me? All right.
I'm going to come to you after seven
days. Go ahead. and show thee what thou
shalt do,
>> and I'm going to show you what to do
next." Now, those were the directions,
but he had some adversity happen in the
midst of that. Go to 1st Samuel chapter
13.
Verse 10. My bad.
1st Samuel 10. Pick it up at verse 10.
Go ahead.
>> And when they came thither to the hill,
behold, a company of prophets met him,
and the spirit of God came upon him, and
he prophesied among them. So Saul had
the spirit of God on him, right? The
Lord is definitely working with him. All
right. 1st Samuel 13.
I'm going pick it up at verse one.
So this situation that we about to read
about, it's a war going on. All right.
But you know, war killing it could get
get real nasty, real scary. But we want
to see, we want to look at how Saul
handles that adversity. And what does
that say about him being the king? Is he
a strong king? Was he a weak king? Verse
one, go ahead.
>> Saul reigned one year, and when he had
reigned two years over Israel, Saul
chose him 3,000 men of Israel, whereof
2,000 were with Saul in Mcmash, and in
Mount Bethl, and a thousand were with
Jonathan in Gibia of
>> Benjamin.
>> And the rest of the people, he sent
every man to his tent.
>> Verse three. And Jonathan smoked the
garrison of the Philistines that was in
Ga. And the Philistines heard of it.
>> So he didn't killed their homes.
Jonathan killed their homes. So they
trying to get their get back. Go ahead.
>> And Saul blew the trumpet throughout the
all the land saying, "Let the Hebrews
hear." And all Israel heard say that
Saul had smitten a garrison of the
Philistines, and that Israel also was
had an abomination with the Philistines.
They upset and the Philistines trying to
they trying to do some do some bad to
Israel. Go ahead.
>> And the people were called together
after Saul to Gilgal.
>> Verse five.
>> And the Philistines gathered themselves
together to fight with Israel, 30,000
chariots and 6,000 horsemen and people
as the sand which is on the seashore in
multitudes.
>> It's pretty much similar to what we read
in Exodus, right? You you got some you
got some some people trying to do some
harm to you, right? All right. So, what
you going to do? You got all It said as
people and the people as the sand which
is on the seashore. That's a lot of
people, a lot of soldiers trying to go
fight you. But Saul, you got the spirit
of the Lord. The Lord is on your side.
What are you going to do in this
situation? Verse six. But no, finish uh
finish the end of verse five.
>> And they came up and pitched in Mcmash
eastward from Beth Haven.
>> Go ahead. When the men of Israel saw
that they were in a straight,
>> so hold on. The word straight, that's
right there. I Googled it. That means a
condition of difficulty. So it's no
doubt that they they in some adversity
right now.
>> They in some trouble. Go ahead.
>> For the people were distressed.
>> So now they they distressed. They they
going through it emotionally. Right.
Now go ahead. Then the people did hide
themselves in caves and in thickets and
in rocks and in high places and in pits.
>> So they h the people are hiding. Go
ahead. Verse seven.
>> And some of the Hebrews went over Jordan
to the land of Gad and Gilead. As for
Saul, he was yet in Gilgl and all the
people followed him trembling.
>> So now imagine if you in a leadership
position, you the you you are the man
with the staff. The people are scared.
They trembling. But what are you going
to do when you in that position when you
got eyes on you? You your kids watching
you and seeing how you handle your
tribulations.
What are you going to do? Are you going
to fold or you going to praise the Lord
in the midst of that? Are you going to
strengthen them or are you going to let
their emotions cling on to you?
Verse eight.
>> And he terried seven days according to
the set time that Samuel had appointed.
>> So now we see this prophecy coming to
pass, right? He went to Gilgal, stayed
there for seven days. But let's see if
he had faith to wait it out. Go ahead.
>> But Samuel came not to Gilgal. And the
people were scattered from him.
>> Uhoh. So now he waiting. He there. He at
the spot. But ain't no telling what he
thinking, what's going on. Probably
people in his ear telling him stuff,
right? He reading.
>> And Saul said, "Bring hither a burnt
offering to me and peace offerings." And
he offered the burnt offering.
>> Is that what Samuel told him to do
initially? No, it wasn't. Definitely
wasn't. He was supposed to wait on
Samuel. The Lord brought you through
those other three prophecies. So why he
can't bring you through this one? That's
because some Philistines are chasing you
and on your back. Verse 10.
>> And it came to pass that as soon as he
had made an end of offering, the the
burnt offering, behold, Samuel came.
Anybody ever went through something and
you tried to handle it yourself and then
the Lord had to show you like kind of
knock you on your head like
>> let me handle that. You stay out the
way. That's pretty much what happened.
The Lord had already told him what to
do. So why are you why are you trying to
be your own salvation? Let the Lord do
that for you. Said he's our strength,
not you. You ain't got no strength.
Finish that.
>> And Saul went out to meet him that he
might salute him. So let's see what
happens when you lean on your own
understanding. Verse 11.
>> And Samuel said, "What hast thou done?"
And Saul said, "Because I saw that the
people were scattered from me, and that
thou camest not within the days
appointed, and that the Philistines
gathered themselves together at Mcmash."
>> In other words, I was scared. I didn't
have any patience, so I wanted to handle
the situation myself. Keep reading.
>> Therefore said I, the Philistines will
come down now upon me to Gilgal.
>> Oh, and I didn't have any faith. Go
ahead.
>> And I have not made supplication unto
the Lord. I forced myself therefore and
offered a burnt offering.
>> You can't force a blessing. If the Lord
going to bless you, he got to do it his
way. You can't force it. So why not just
sit back and let it play out? 13
>> And Samuel said to Saul, "Thou has done
foolishly.
Thou has not kept the commandment of the
Lord thy God, which he commanded thee.
For now would the Lord have established
thy kingdom upon Israel forever."
>> So you were supposed to have your sons
come up after you and be king. It didn't
have to be David, but because of your
disobedience,
you you the last one in your generation
to be king. That's why it went from Saul
to David and then from David to Solomon,
so forth and so on. Verse 14.
>> But now thy kingdom shall not continue.
The Lord had sought him a man after his
own heart, and the Lord had commanded
him to be captain over his people,
because thou has not kept that which the
Lord commanded thee.
>> And I'm going to tell you this, if you
in a leadership position, the Lord ain't
got no room for no weak leader. Don't
don't when David rolled up on the scene
and just think about how logical
illogical that is a grown man talking
about Goliath been a warrior since his
youth and Saul and his people allowed
David to go and fight that trained
warrior. What type of what was Saul on
have to do that? It had to be the Lord
cuz you know that's like me sending one
of the teams to go fight Debo or
something like that. like that ain't
something that just happened. But when
you got that spirit of the Lord in you
and we saw David wasn't scared. He was
fighting lions and bears like you know
with his bare hands. So he had that
spirit of the Lord in him. David didn't
have no fear. Saul had that fear and the
Lord ultimately he was done with Saul.
And we know what happened with Saul. We
know his end. But
what does your situation say about you?
Come here. You keep the Sabbath, keep
the feast, do outreach, but when you go
through your own situations, are you
praying to the Lord? Are you bitter
pointing the finger at other people
because of the things you're going
through? Or are you on your knees
praying? Are you searching your Bible to
find answers? Or just being patient and
waiting on the Lord to show you show you
something?
Let's go to Romans chapter 5.
Romans chapter 5.
Going to pick it up at verse one.
We're going to do some skipping.
Romans chapter 5.
Go ahead. Pick it up at verse one, bro.
>> Therefore, being justified by faith, we
have peace with God through our Lord
Jesus Christ.
>> How do we have peace with God? Go ahead.
Verse three.
And not only so, but we glor but but we
glory in tribulations also, knowing that
tribulation workketh patience.
>> So when you faint in the day of your
adversity, this is what you miss out on.
You miss out on those growth
opportunities because when you're going
through tribulation, it gives you
patience. It teach you how to be
patience. How to be patient. Verse four.
>> And patience experience. And when you
when you've been through something
multiple times, you gain experience and
understand that you know what, this just
a hard time. It's a bad moment. I'd have
been through bad moments before. The
Lord got me. He going to protect me. I
mean, we read in Ecclesiastes is ups and
downs in life anyway. So, you get
experience from from practicing that
patience. All right. Go ahead.
>> And experience hope. And then you just
you you get hope. You know that there's
going to be a end goal to that thing.
you ain't going to have your uh bills be
a problem forever. Like I said, with
them taxes here, I know it relieved a
lot of people. I was relieved after them
getting them taxes. So, you know, I
praise the Lord. So, we just got to keep
it keep that in mind like it's going to
be some hope at the end of that. Verse
five,
>> and hope make it not ashamed.
>> And you got confident, confidence,
because you know, you pretty much know
that cycle. I go through some
tribulation. I just got to be patient.
If I'm patient, I learn something from
that experience, right? And then I have
hope because I know that the Lord is
going to protect. He going to see me
through it. Finish verse five.
>> Because the love of God is shed abroad
in our hearts by the Holy Ghost which is
given unto us.
>> So now we didn't looked at adversity and
what it says about your character
depending on how you deal with it. But
this is one thing that you really got to
keep in mind. Who was Saul being an
example for when he folded under
pressure? Think about what what the
people under him thought. Was he
impactful to them? Was he um encouraging
them or encouraging to them? Or was he
just showing a sign of having a lack of
faith? So, let's go to second
Corinthians chapter 1.
God uses your affliction not just to
punish you or not just to put you
through something, but he uses it so you
can help other people. So, you can have
a testimony to share to somebody who's
going through the same situation that
that that you've been through.
So don't always look at like why me or
me this or me that. No, maybe the Lord
is just using you as an example.
Second Corinthians chapter 1, give me
verse three.
Go ahead.
Blessed be God, even the father of our
Lord Jesus Christ, the father of mercies
and the God of all comfort. And
>> we know that God can comfort you. We
read examples about how he can give you
comfort. All right. Verse four.
>> Who comforted us in all our tribulation.
>> But why? Go ahead.
>> That we may be able to comfort them
which are in any trouble by the comfort
wherewith we ourselves are comforted of
God.
>> So in other words, God will deliver you
from your situation so that you can
deliver somebody else. So think about it
when like I keep going back to bills,
but every it's something everybody can
relate to. If you had problems paying
your rent and this person got problems
paying their rent, well, you done made
it through the other side. So, you can
show them some light on how they can get
through it. If you having problems with
your kids, you can help somebody else
deal with their issues with their kids.
So, that's just how it works. We're
supposed to strengthen one another. Go
to um Luke 20 Luke chapter 22. My bad.
Verse 5. Go ahead. For as the sufferings
of Christ abound in us, so our
consolation also abounded by Christ.
>> So just like them sufferings, they
increase, increase, increase, your
comfort should also increase in the Lord
as well. And look, I've done it. I've
been there before. I've had to go to my
brothers and go to the elders to have
them pray for me because I didn't have
it within myself to to pray my way out
or to whatever it was. I had to go, you
know, seek my brothers to help. So is
you not in this you're not in this walk
alone. But I even stand before you today
just to show you that the Lord will see
you through and your story can help
somebody else. Luke 22,
Luke chapter 22, I want verse 31-32.
All right. Luke chapter 22,
give me verse 31. When you get there, go
ahead and read.
>> And the Lord said, Simon, Simon, behold,
Satan had desired to have you, that he
may sift you as wheat, but I have prayed
for thee, that thy faith fail not, and
when thou are converted, strengthen thy
brethren.
>> If you fold at every sign of pressure,
you won't be able to help nobody else.
You have to be a strong individual to
help somebody else. You can't. So you
you can't like and I'm not I'm not
saying that it doesn't happen like we
don't get sad, we don't cry, we don't
get frustrated at our situations. But in
the midst of that, is there some type of
prayer that you that you're doing? Is
there some type of you watching lessons,
reading your Bible? Are you doing
something to help get yourself out of
that affliction? Or are you just soaking
in that and just just blaming the world?
Because then, okay, if you're a
Christian, then how you going to help
somebody else? How are you going to be
an example to somebody else of how to
get out of that affliction?
Let's go to James chapter 5.
And that's why the Lord gave us this
book. All these prophets wrote all these
different things that that happened to
him. All these different afflictions.
Even Jesus, we understand that Jesus
went through a lot of suffering. He
didn't come into this world to have
pleasure.
He came to die for the sins of mankind.
That if that ain't adversity, I don't
know what it is.
long suffering. That's right, bro. James
chapter 5, pick it up at verse 10.
Go ahead.
>> Take my brethren, the prophets who have
spoken in the name of the Lord for an
example of suffering, affliction, and of
patience.
>> So, you're not alone. And that's the
great thing about God. He teaches you
things. So, we got the prophets to teach
us how to how to get through how to
suffer affliction. We looked at um
Exodus. We looked at Moses in Israel. We
looked at Job. We started off with Job
looking at how he endured his
affliction. Then we looked at Saul
showing what not to do. So, we got all
these different written examples of how
to suffer affliction. Verse 11,
>> behold, we count them happy which
endure. That's right.
>> Ye have heard of the patience of Job and
have seen the end of the Lord, that the
Lord is very pitiful and of tender
mercy.
>> See, that's the thing that we lose sight
on. We lose sight that of what the end
of the Lord is. What is that blessing
after that storm?
We seen three examples of the Lord can
something happened behind the scenes and
the Lord letting it play out and then
you in the middle of that affliction.
You got a moment where you can either
hold fast or you fail. If you fail, you
going to miss that blessing on the
opposite end. Let's go to Job 42. We
going we going I got uh one more spot
after this, but we going to you know we
started with Job. We going to finish
with Job.
So we understand how how Job he was in
the last time we read about Job. He was
definitely doing bad.
But let's look at how the Lord blessed
him after his season of hardship.
Job chapter 42,
going pick it up at verse one.
Go ahead. Then Job answered the Lord and
said, I know that thou can do everything
and that no thought can be withholden
from thee. Who is he that hideth counsel
without knowledge? Therefore have I
uttered that I understood not things too
wonderful for me which I knew not.
>> So if you read over the course of this
whole chapter, this whole book, Job is
is he's speaking from a lack of
understanding. The Lord ends up showing
up and he pretty much tell Job like
look, you don't know what you're talking
about. So he enlightens him on some
things. So now that he got
understanding, his perspective changed
on his affliction. Verse four,
>> here and I beseech thee, and I will
speak. I will demand of thee, and
declare thou unto me.
>> Verse five,
>> I have heard of thee by the hearing of
the ear, but now mine eyes seeth thee.
>> Sometimes we hear these scriptures and
just kind of it go in one ear, out the
other. But until you got to actually
live out this book, then you truly get
understanding of how how good God is.
>> Verse six,
>> wherefore I abhore myself and repent in
dust and ashes.
>> Now skip to verse 10.
>> And the Lord turned the captivity of Job
when he prayed for his friends. Also,
the Lord gave Job twice as much as he
had before.
>> Now, let me ask this question. When you
going through something,
are you humble enough to
look at somebody else and pray for them
while you going through it?
>> If you having those same financial
problems, are you praying for somebody
else to have some prosperity?
Or are you just focused on what you
going through and what you dealing with
as if you the only one that got problems
in the world?
But Job prayed for his friends. And it
said after and the Lord turned the
captivity of Job when he prayed for his
friends and he said the L he was blessed
with twice twice as much he had before.
Keep reading. Then came there unto him
all his brethren and all his sisters and
all they that had been of his
acquaintance before and did eat bread
with him in his house. and they bemoaned
him and comforted him over all the evil
that the Lord had brought upon him.
>> Every man also gave him a piece of money
and everyone an airing of gold. But when
he was going through his trouble, that
was just his season of affliction. He
had to go through that. He couldn't
avoid it. But after the fact, now he's
being comforted. Now he's being
restored.
Uh 12. So the Lord blessed the latter
end of Job more than his beginning,
>> for he had 14,000 sheep and 6,000 camels
and a thousand yolk of oxen and a
thousand sheazes.
>> So now he's back in a season of increase
and he got understanding to go with it
that okay, it was just a bad season. The
Lord got me through it. Do you say the
same thing for yourself when you going
through your situations? Where we at? 13
>> 13
>> He had also seven sons and three
daughters.
>> He had more kids. Keep reading.
>> And he called the name of the first
Jamaima, and the name of the second
Kazia, and the name of the third, Karen
Hapak.
And in all the land were no woman found
so fair as the daughters of Job. And
their father gave them inheritance among
their brethren. So we see now we went
through all that trouble just to see now
where Job is getting he's getting
blessed now.
Read verse 16.
>> After this live Job 140 years
>> so he lived a long time. Go ahead.
>> And saw his sons and his son's sons even
four generations.
>> Imagine the blessing in that. Imagine
the stories you can tell your children
your your children's children. you went
through this and the Lord brought you
through because you know your kids going
your kids got to go through adversity
too. So they need to know how to handle
it when they when it when it shows up in
their life.
>> 17.
>> So Job died being old and full of days.
>> That's right. So let's go to my last
spot. First Peter chapter 1. And this
the message I want to leave y'all with
today.
There's always a blessing at the end of
a hard season.
You just got to remind yourself that 1
Peter chapter 1 going to pick it up at
verse 6.
1 Peter uh 1 me verse 6-9. Go ahead.
Wherein ye greatly rejoice though now
for a season if need be. Ye are ye are
in heaviness through manifold
temptations.
>> So even though you're going through
these temptations and this suffering,
try to rejoice in it because you can
look back at it and look and see that
the Lord brought you through it. I've
done it before. When I look at
everything that it took for me to get
here to teach before y'all, it wasn't
easy. It wasn't. I had to go through a
lot. You know, a lot of um I started
reading now.
The brothers tell me I complain too much
about how it was when me starting
cleaning up. So
if you know, you know. If you know, you
know. I'm going just say I had to go
through a lot of affliction to get up
here and share my experience and you
know to share the word of God with you
guys up here. Keep reading. that the
trial of your faith being much more
precious than of gold that perisheth,
>> though it be tried with fire, might be
found unto praise and honor and glory at
the appearing of Jesus Christ.
>> So, in other words, yes, you're going to
be tried. You're going to be broken
down, but the Lord is going to build you
up to somebody who is worthy for the
kingdom. That's why this this this thing
about life, you got to know how to
endure adversity.
Oh yeah. Verse eight.
>> Whom having not seen ye love and whom
though now ye see him not yet believing
ye rejoice with joy unspeakable and full
of glory. Receiving the end of your
faith.
>> That's right.
>> Even the salvation of your souls.
>> So look at the end of your faith. The
end of you getting through this life.
Whether you make it to the great
tribulation or you you die. But if you
hold fast in this thing, keep your faith
in the Lord, you get salvation.
Who wouldn't want that? That's the
lesson. I thank you for your time.
You
got
heat.